Guide to the Winkler Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Correspondence
  - FROM AND TO VARIOUS AUTHORS, A-Z
    - Unger-Sabatier, Karolina, 1805-1877. ALS to ?, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 198)
      3 p. Opera singer, known by her stage name Carlotta Ungher. A letter of recommendation for the baritone Haimer who wishes a guest engagement at the Dresden Opera
    - Wieland, Christoph Martin, 1733-1813. 2 ALS to Carl Leonhard Reinhold, Weimar, 1795-96 (Box 3, Folder 199)
      20 p. First letter signed: Reinhold von Wieland's son-in-law; second letter unsigned. The letter of 1795 includes a discussion of the French revolution; mentions Baggesen, Fichte, Göschen and Herder; relates chiefly to Weiland's son Ludwig, who is coming to stay with his sister Sophie and brother-in-law at Kiel. The letter of 1796 contains the description of a journey to Switzerland where Weiland visited his daughter Charlotte who was married to Heinrich Gessner; mentions Konrad Gessner and Hottinger and includes a characterization of Lavater. Folder containing a biographical sketch of Weiland in an unidentified hand, and 6 newspaper clippings from the years 1881-84, 5 mounted containing short articles on Weiland
    - Winkler, Eugenia Agathe (Schaff), 1804-1853. ALS to her daughter Dora, 1851 Mar 5 (Box 3, Folder 200)
      1 p. Apparently written in anticipation of Winkler's fiftieth anniversary of association with the Hoftheater at Dresden. On verso of the letter, in a different hand, the poem Blumen an den König, composed for the occasion by Princess Amalia of Saxony
    - Unidentified to Unidentified. 2 ALS, 1833, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 200a)
- Writings
  - WORKS AND LETTERS BY WINKLER
    - ALS to unidentified publisher, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 201)
      1 p. Promising a contribution to a proposed Taschenbuch
    - ALS to unidentified lady, 1841 Nov 15 (Box 3, Folder 202)
      1 p. Signed: Karl Winkler
    - ALS to his daughter Dora, Teplitz, 1855 Aug 1 (Box 3, Folder 203)
      4 p. Signed: Karl Winkler
    - 10 autograph poems, chiefly directed to his wife, [1822]-29 (Box 3, Folder 204)
      16 p. One signed: Karl; all others unsigned Pencil note at head of first poem: Glücks Ahnung einer Frau. An Louise S. Contents [first lines]: Welch ein Himmelsthau - Einen Kranz lass heut dir winden - Süsses Weibchen, holdes Leben - Seitdem schon der dritte Ring - Und der vierte Ring, mein Leben - Gute, liebe, treue Seele - Gottlob! Da gehn die Sterne auf - Unter dieses Klosters Drümmern - Einsam weilest du in der Zelle - Und ich hab der Verse so viele geschrieben.
    - Mein Dank, poem. Autograph ms. (facsim.), 1851 (Box 3, Folder 205)
      3 p. In appreciation of the honors and festivities dedicated to him at the fiftieth anniversary of his membership in the Grosse Landes-Loge von Saschen. Begins with: Wie nun euch danken?
    - Ein Blick aus dem Fenster; An meine Kinder. Typescript (carbon), 1850 Feb 7 (Box 3, Folder 206)
      13 p. Winkler's reminiscences of friends and associates who lived in the various houses around the Altmark in Dresden during Winkler's residence there. On page 13 a plan of the plaza by O. Stadlinger with a short description of the site as of March 1936
  - WORKS, ETC. BY VARIOUS AUTHORS
    - Balzac, Honoré de, 1799-1850. Autograph quotation from Napoléon, Dresden, 1840 May 9 (Box 3, Folder 207)
      1 p. Signed: de Balzac "En toute chose la puissance de l'inconnu est incommensurable (Napoléon)" On verso of page a penciled note: Der Referendar von Reinhardt bittet Herrn Commissions Rath [name illegible].. ein freundschaftliche Suppe bei ihm einnehmen zu wollen
    - Böttinger, Karl August, 1760-1835. 3 autograph poems written for Elisa von der Recke, signed: Bottiger, Dresden, 1823-28 (Box 3, Folder 208)
      7 p. 1. Der hochherzigen Elise am Neujahrsmorgen 1823. [Wünsche am Neujahrstag gleichen.] 2. Zum algefeierten[!] Theresientage am 20ten Mai 1824 [Versammelt euch, Guitarren und Schalmeien.] 3. Der ehrwürdigsten unter Deutschlands Frauen Elisa von der Recke.. zum 20 Mai 1828 [Dass Gleiches sich zu Gleichem stets gesellt]
    - Brennin, Frau. Die Brennin an Ihren Mann im Felde [poem], n.d. (Box 3, Folder 209)
      2 p. Begins: Ich weibisch seyn ?
    - Chezy, Wilhelmine Christiane (von Klencke) von, 1786-1856. Die Ankunft in Pillnitz [poem] Autograph ms. in unidentified hand, 1841 (Box 3, Folder 210)
      2 p. Dated: "Oberwiessenfeld 12 Sept. 1842, Helmina v. Chezy geb. v. Klencke." Begins: Maria, Lust der Herzen
    - Chezy, Wilhelmine Christiane (von Klencke) von, 1786-1856. Glaube, Hoffnung, Liebe, 1841 Sep 29 (Box 3, Folder 211)
      1 p. With superscription: Helmina Begins: In Dank nun glüh'n die Herzen
    - [Ende, Otto Baron von] Notizen zu meiner Reise von Etwa 14 Tagen. Autograph ms., fragment, 1836 (Box 3, Folder 212)
      4 p. Travelling in Scotland
    - Geibel, Emanuel, 1815-1884. Erster Sonnenblick. Minnelied [2 poems] Autograph ms., signed, 1833 (Box 3, Folder 213)
      4 p. The first poem begins: Nach so viel trüben, trüben Nebeltagen; the second: Es giebt wohl manches was entzücket. Published in his Gesammelte Werke, Stuttgart 1833, 1 Bd., p. 147-48, 185-88, respectively
    - Glück, Barbara Elisabeth, 1814-1894. Wunsch [poem], n.d. (Box 3, Folder 214)
      1 p. Begins: Nimmer werde mir ein Glück gegeben
    - Hoffmann, Ernest Theodor Amadeus, 1777-1822. [Fantasiestückeain Callot's Manier. Fragment] Autograph ms., n.d. (Box 3, Folder 215)
      3 p. Marginal note in another hand: E.T.W. Hoffmann's Handschrift, nach welcher der Druck der Fantasiestücke, lte Aufl. geschah. Published in his Ausgewählte Werke, Berlin, 1827, v. 7, Phantasiestücke, p.61-64, 402
    - Hülle, Hedwig, 1794-1861. An die Helden dieser Zeit [poem] Autograph ms. (Box 3, Folder 216)
      2 p. Begins Hellas weint - ein trüber Schleier. Published in her Erstlinge des Frühlings, Bremen, 1822
    - Kerner, Justinus Andreas Christian, 1786-1862. Die ächte Thräne [poem] Autograph ms. signed. Weinsberg, 1845 Aug 18 (Box 3, Folder 217)
      1 p. Published in his Sämtliche poetische Werke, Leipzig 1905, vol. 1, p.78
    - Meissner, August Gottlieb, 1753-1807. Autograph list of manuscript letters, etc. used in preparation for a biography of Johann Gottlieb Naumann, Loebichau, 1802 Apr 10 (Box 3, Folder 218)
      2 p. The biography was published at Prague in 1803
    - Saint-Léon, Charles Victor Arthur, 1821-1870. 2 autograph musical motifs dedicated to Fanny Cerrito Saint Léon, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 219)
      1 p. French violinist, dancer, choreographer and composer; pupil of Paganini; in 1845 he married Fanny Cerrito
    - Schink, Johann Friedrich, 1755-1835. Dem zoten Mai 1820. An Elise [poem], Sagan, 1828 May 1 (Box 3, Folder 220)
      1 p. Begins: Blüthen brachte der Mond
    - Schink, Johann Friedrich, 1755-1835. Den gebeugten eltern [poem], Berlin, 1826 Dec 28 (Box 3, Folder 221)
      2 p. Apparently directed to KGTW and his wife at the death of their son. Begins: Unter den dunkelen Früchten
    - Weber, Michael, 1754-1833. Autograph note, in Latin, of lectures to be held by him, 1827 May 4 (Box 3, Folder 222)
    - Winkler, Eugenia Agathe (Schaff), 1804-1853. [Autograph copy of one poem each by Schiller, Heine und Ida Hahn-hahn] (Box 3, Folder 223)
      2 p. Contents. - Von Schiller an Gräfin von Kuhnheim, geb.v.Arnim. (Ein treffend Bild von diesem Leben). - Anfangs wollt ich fast verzagen. Heinrich Heine. - Die Zukunt's gehört uns nur in Tränen.. was du treibst und was du übst. Ida Hahn-Hahn. Note at the end of Schiller's poem: Noch ungedruckt. Schiller's poem published in his Sämtliche Werke, Leipzig, 1910, v.3. page 231-232, with title: An Henriette Elisabeth von Arnim
    - Zachariä von Lingenthal, Karl Solomon, 1769-1843. ALS to "Rectori Academia Magnifico", Wittenberg, 1803 Sep 13 (Box 3, Folder 224)
      1 p. Reproving the rectors for leaving his proposal concerning the candidacy of D.Klein and Lauter unanswered and requesting the return of his vote for the candidate Lauter
    - Programm zur Fünfzigjährigen Jubelfeier des Herrn Hofrath C.TH. Winkler. Vicedirektor und Sekretair des Köigl. Hoftheaters, 1851 Mar 10 (Box 3, Folder 225)
      5 p. With red underlinings
    - Unidentified. Motto and a quote copied by an unidentified person (Box 3, Folder 225a)
- Printed Material and Photographs, 1851 Mar 10
  - An Carl Winkler. Dresden, 1851 Mar 10 (Box 3, Folder 226)
    2 p. A printed poem signed: Carl. A tribute at the fiftieth anniversary of his connection with the Dresden Theater.
  - Freemasons. Saxony. Grosse Landes- Loge von Sachsen, Dresden (Box 3, Folder 227)
    Protocoll über die fünfzigjährige Maurer-Jubel-Feier des ehrwürdigsten Br. Carl Gottfried Theodor Winkler, Grossmeisters der Grossen Landes-Loge von Sachsen und Meisters vom Stuhl der Vereinten Loge zu den drei Schwertern und Asträa zur grünenden Raute im Orient Dresden, und über die von demselben.. vollzogene Aufnahme seines Sohnes Eugen Winkler in den Maurerbund am 21. Februar 1854. Dresden, gedruckt bei'm Br. Ramming [1854] 56 pages includes poems
  - Schütze, Martin, 1866- Der Briefwechsel zwischen Lavater und Elisa von der Recke: Neuentdeckte Originale [New York, Columbia University Press], 1932 (Box 3, Folder 228)
    Reprinted from The Germanic Review, v.7.
  - Sonetten-Kranz für Theodor Hell [pseud.] Gewunden zum neunten Februar 1827 von einem seiner innigsten Verehrer. Dresden, Arnold'sche Buchhandling (Box 3, Folder 229)
    10 p.
  - Weber, Karl Maria Friedrich Ernst, freiherr von, 1786-1826 Printed circular letter to all theaters concerning his property rights of the opera Oberon., n.d. (Box 3, Folder 230)
    [2] p. One addressed to "Theater- Direction zu Bamberg" and the other to the "Direction des Kaiserlichen Deutschen Theaters zu Petersburg", both were refused and returned to Weber
  - Winkler, Karl Gottfried Theodor, 1775-1856. Meiner Theodora, 1847 Jan 15 (Box 3, Folder 231)
    2 p. A printed poem at the occasion of his daughter's marriage.
  - Winkler, Karl Gottfried Theodor, 1775-1856. Selbstprüfung am Vorabend meines fünfzigjährigen Jubelfestes als Staatsdiener., 1851 Mar 10 (Box 3, Folder 232)
    [4] p. A printed poem, signed KGTW Begins: Schwebet nieder, Genien der Stunden
  - Documents pertaining to the Winkler family, 1644-51 (Box 3, Folder 233)
    6 pieces. Contents, 2 genealogical tables of the Winkler family, covering the period of 1490-1856, the date of KGTW's death, negative photostat of a patent of guardianship for Regina Winkler, dated 1644, and, on the same leaf, of a contract of property sale to David Winkler, dated 1644, with receipts of 1651 and 1649, Negative photostat of a contract of a house sale between Martha, widow of Georg Winkler, and Gregor Metz; incomplete and undated, Typed copy, on one leaf, of a birth certificate of Peter Winkler, 1702, David Winkler, 1709, and a marriage certificate of Hans and Maria (Höhne) Winkler, 1689, Typed copy of genealogical data of the Schaff family, taken from the tomb stones in the old Neustadt cemetery
  - 13 photographs pertaining to the Winkler family, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 234)
    Photographs of two portraits of KGTW and of one of his wife, Eugenia (Schaff) Winkler Original pencil drawing of the Archdeaconry Waldenburg
- Martin Schütze. Notes on the Winkler Letters, n.d.
  - Schütze, Martin, 1866- Autograph notes preparatory to a printed edition of the letters to KGTW and Elisa von der Recke (Box 3, Folder 235)
    In ink and pencil Includes a list of source material With copies of two poems by Goethe and of two letters by Casanova from the originals formerly in the possession of Mr. and Mrs. Alfred E. Hamill except for an exchange of letters between Johann Caspar Lavater and Elisa von der Recke, the letters were not published